Luther Burbank Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Luther Burbank Papers 1830-1989 (bulk 1880-1926)
MSS14324
Burbank, Luther, 1849-1926
12,500 items
41 containers
16 linear feet
2 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Botanist, horticulturist, and naturalist. Correspondence, speeches and writings, notes, sketches, nursery plans and notes, business records, scrapbooks, family papers and genealogies, and printed material concerning Burbank's career as a botanist and his family and personal life.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bailey, L. H. (Liberty Hyde), 1858-1954--Correspondence.; Bean, Burt C. (Burt Clifford), 1874-; Burbank family.; Burbank, Luther, 1849-1926.; Burpee, W. Atlee (Washington Atlee), 1858-1915--Correspondence.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931--Correspondence.; Fairchild, David, 1869-1954--Correspondence.; Firestone, Harvey Samuel, 1868-1938--Correspondence.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947--Correspondence.; Husbands, José D.--Correspondence.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931--Correspondence.; Keller, Helen, 1880-1968--Correspondence.; Kellogg, Vernon L. (Vernon Lyman), 1867-1937--Correspondence.; Kinsey, Alfred C. (Alfred Charles), 1894-1956--Correspondence.; Lemmon, J. G. (John Gill), 1832-1908--Correspondence.; London, Charmian--Correspondence.; London, Jack, 1876-1916--Correspondence.; Miller, Joaquin, 1837-1913--Correspondence.; Morrow, William W., 1843-1929--Correspondence.; Muir, John, 1838-1914--Correspondence.; Samu, Spiegel--Correspondence.; Schull, George H.--Correspondence.; Vachell, F. Harvey--Correspondence.; Van Deman, Henry Elias, 1845-1915--Correspondence.; Vries, Hugo de, 1848-1935--Correspondence.; Waugh, F. A. (Frank Albert), 1869-1943--Correspondence.; Wickson, Edward J. (Edward James), 1848-1923--Correspondence.; Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1850-1919--Correspondence.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924--Correspondence.; Woodward, Robert Simpson, 1849-1924--Correspondence.
Organizations
Alaska-Yukon-Pacific Exposition (1909: Seattle, Wash.); Panama-Pacific International Exposition (1915: San Francisco, Calif.)
Subjects
Botany.; Horticulture.; Nurseries (Horticulture)--California--Santa Rosa.; Plants.
Occupations
Botanists; Horticulturists.
Provenance
The papers of Luther Burbank, botanist, horticulturist and naturalist, were given to the Library of Congress by the estate of Elizabeth Waters Burbank in 1978. Selected items microfilmed by the Library of Congress were retained by the city of Santa Rosa, California, for display in the Luther Burbank Home. A small addition was given to the Library in 1992 by Renee Felciano.
Additional Guides
The Luther Burbank Papers have been partially described in the Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress, vol. 36, Oct. 1979, pp. 423-427.
Transfers
Prints and photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Luther Burbank are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
Two reels of microfilm are included as part of the Burbank Papers. This microfilm consists of reproductions of items retained by the city of Santa Rosa, California, for display in the Luther Burbank Home and is not available for interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1849, Mar. 7 Born, Lancaster, Mass.
1871 Opened plant nursery in Lunenburg, Mass.
1871 1875 Developed the Burbank potato
1875 Moved to Santa Rosa, Calif.
1890 Married Helen Coleman (divorced 1896)
1893 Published first descriptive seed catalog, New Creations
1904 1906 Visiting lecturer, Stanford University, Stanford, Calif.
1905 1910 Awarded $10,000 annual stipend by the Carnegie Institution of Washington, Washington, D.C.
1914 1915 Published Luther Burbank, His Methods and Discoveries and Their Practical Application (New York: Luther Burbank Press. 12 vols.)
1916 Married Elizabeth Waters
1926, Apr. 11 Died, Santa Rosa, Calif.
1927 Posthumous publication with Wilbur Hall of The Harvest of the Years (Boston: Houghton Mifflin. 296 pp.)
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Luther Burbank (1849-1926) span the years 1830-1989, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1880-1926. Known to many of his generation as "the plant wizard," Burbank was popularly classed among the scientific heroes of the early twentieth century. His collection consists of the following series: Family Papers, General Correspondence, Speeches and Writings File, Notes and Sketches, Business Records, Miscellany, an Addition, and a Microfilm series consisting of a small selection of items from the papers which were retained by the city of Santa Rosa, California, for display in the Luther Burbank Home.
The Family Papers series includes a variety of records predating Burbank's birth in Lancaster, Massachusetts, and continuing well after his death in the Northern California town of Santa Rosa. Especially valuable are letters Burbank exchanged with his mother and sister while a prospective emigrant to the West Coast in 1875. The earliest family correspondence, dated as early as 1850, is mostly in the form of typewritten transcripts by Burbank's second wife, Elizabeth Waters Burbank, or by one of his biographers. The transcripts reproduce letters from and between Burbank's brothers and father supplemented by legal, biographical, and other personal data. Also in the Family Papers is travel memorabilia which includes a brief diary by Burbank of a trip to his boyhood New England in 1888. Since Burbank's sister, two brothers, and mother had joined or preceded him in his move to California, his journeys outside the state account for practically all of his family correspondence after 1878.
The General Correspondence series is extensive and, in addition to carbons or drafts of Burbank's replies, contains personal as well as professional letters. There are diverse and sometimes substantive inquiries from farmers interested in his projects, requests for seed catalogs from other nurserymen, fact-finding reports by foreign nationals intent on supplying Burbank with unusual seeds or seedlings, and a great deal of adulatory "fan" mail from friends both prominent and obscure. Burbank wrote and received letters from Harvey S. Firestone, Henry Ford, Charmian London, Joaquin Miller, John Muir, and Ella Wheeler Wilcox. The largest part of the correspondence concerns scientists and government officials who shared his training or helped in communicating the results of his research. Among the more significant of these individuals were David Starr Jordan, friend and patron at Stanford University, and Robert S. Woodward, head of the Carnegie Institution of Washington when Burbank was funded by that body to free him from the ordinary tasks of nursery administration.
Other scientists whose correspondence appears with some frequency include Liberty Hyde Bailey, David G. Fairchild, Jose D. Husbands, Vernon L. Kellogg, George H. Schull, H. E. Van Deman, and Hugo De Vries. The letters from De Vries are of particular interest, since it was the Dutch botanist's generous writings about Burbank's Santa Rosa experiments which broadcast their significance to the academic and scientific community. California booster organizations, then in their peak phase, also took an active part in the promotion of the plant breeder's achievements, and the evidence of their contact is best seen in the correspondence between Burbank and various officials of state and county chambers of commerce, the Alaska-Yukon-Pacific Exposition in Seattle of 1909, the Panama-Pacific International Exposition in San Francisco in 1915, and the California State Boards of Horticulture and Agriculture.
As a celebrated discoverer of new plant varieties, Burbank depended less on strict scientific methodology than on a prodigious ability to test and experiment on a practical, empirical basis. Although he made sporadic efforts to keep comprehensive records of his research, he often destroyed them once a product was finished. Those accounts which still exist have been organized in a Notes and Sketches series and complement typescripts in the Speeches and Writings File containing narrative descriptions of genera and species which he cultivated at his Santa Rosa and Sebastopol nurseries between 1903 and 1911. Among the Business Records are account books, inventories, stock lists, and plan books related to Burbanks studies. This part of the collection, while focusing mainly on financial aspects of the Burbank operation, shows where and how he purchased seeds, the diligence of his propagation and selection, and the layout of his gardens. As is true of the Notes and Sketches, the Business Records are occasionally illustrated with Burbank's drawings of his techniques and products.
The Speeches and Writings File consists of Burbank's personal writings as well as the printed, near-print, and typescript comments of scientists, friends, and journalists. Prominent among the latter were some of his most devoted admirers, including De Vries, Wilbur Hall Jordan, Kellogg, and Edward J. Wickson. In addition, there is a transcript of a 1913 interview with Burbank by Burt C. Bean. The bulk of the Burbank manuscripts pertains to plant descriptions and what is supposed to be a complete series of his published seed catalogs, but there are also a few copies of statements he made on personal and social issues and a small folder of lectures given at Stanford University between 1904 and 1906. At the end of the collection is a Miscellany series of clippings and scrapbooks which include large quantities of ephemera and some important writings.
The Microfilm series consists of selected correspondence, family papers and genealogies, nursery plans and notes, financial records, scrapbooks, and miscellany. Prominent correspondents in the series include Thomas A. Edison, Helen Keller, Alfred C. Kinsey, Jack London, and Woodrow Wilson.
Correspondents in addition to those listed above include W. Atlee Burpee, Herbert G. Gleason, J. G. Lemmon, W. W. Morrow, Spiegel Samu, F. Harvey Vachell, and F. A. Waugh.
Burbank made extensive use of photography to record the course and results of his plant breeding, and a large quantity of prints and negatives, including glass plates, has been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division of the Library of Congress.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eight series:
Family Papers, circa 1830-1969
General Correspondence, 1871-1929
Speeches and Writings File, 1869-1950
Notes and Sketches, 1886-1925
Business Records, 1871-1921
Miscellany, 1894-1922
Addition, 1989
Microfilm, 1864-1964
Container List
- Family Papers, circa 1830-1969 (Box 1-2)
  Letters to and from Burbank's family, including transcriptions of originals not in the collection, and subject files of topical correspondence, legal matters, school reports, travel notes, and other holograph, typewritten, near-print, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent or subject and chronologically therein.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Originals
      - Bell, Jane (sister), 1890-1907, undated
      - Burbank, Elizabeth Waters (wife), 1916-1921, undated
      - Burbank and Ross family (cousins), 1901-1926
      - Burbank family (distant relatives), 1904-1918
    - Transcriptions
      - Burbank Family, 1869-1912, undated
        - Burbank, George (brother), 1850-1863, undated
  - Subject file
    - "The Authorized Biography of Luther Burbank," by Burt C. Bean, 1923-1926
    - Biographical and family material compiled by Elizabeth Waters Burbank, 1915-1949, undated
    - Burbank, Alfred (brother), 1909-1913
    - Centennial of birth, 1949
    - Condolences on Burbank's death, 1926
    - Divorce settlement, 1896
    - Legal documents, 1899-1934
    - Luther Burbank Christmas Memorial, 1947-1948
    - Proposed Luther Burbank Foundation at Stanford University, Stanford, Calif., 1926-1928
    - School and youth, 1865-1949 (Box 2)
    - Spanish documents from South America, originals, copies, and translations, circa 1830-1969
    - Travel
      - Canada, 1894
      - Massachusetts, 1900
      - Raymond's Vacation Excursions, 1888
- General Correspondence, 1871-1929 (Box 2-12)
  Letters with enclosures received by Burbank and drafts or copies of letters sent.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and chronologically therein.
  - American Anti-Alcohol Education Association See Container 5, Hobson, Richard P. (Box 2)
  - Anderson, Ann P., 1906-1911
  - Atherton, Gertrude, 1905-1908, undated
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1894-1926, undated, (3 folders)
  - Bailey, Liberty H., 1891-1907, undated
  - Burpee, W. Atlee, 1896-1917
  - "B" miscellaneous, 1899-1926, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Bonnheim, Albert, 1909 See Container 11, White Crusaders
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington, 1903-1910, (2 folders)
  - "C" miscellaneous
    - 1890-1916, (2 folders)
    - 1917-1926, undated (Box 4)
  - D. Hay and Son, 1887-1899, undated
  - Damman & Co., 1894-1896
  - De Vries, Hugo, 1903-1929
  - Doubleday, Page & Co., 1903-1918
  - "D" miscellaneous, 1889-1926, undated, (2 folders)
  - Empson, J. H., 1905-1921
  - "E" miscellaneous, 1888-1926, undated
  - Fairchild, David G., 1899-1910
  - Firestone, Harvey S., 1917-1923
  - Ford, Henry, and Ford Motor Co., 1915-1928, undated
  - "F" miscellaneous
    - 1891-1912
    - 1913-1926, undated (Box 5)
  - Gleason, Herbert W., 1908-1923, undated
  - Grucy, Lucien (French war orphan and godson), 1919-1923, undated
  - "G" miscellaneous, 1871-1927, undated, (2 folders)
  - Hobson, Richmond P., 1921-1922
  - Husbands, Jose D., 1905-1911, undated, (2 folders)
  - "H" miscellaneous
    - 1891-1906
    - 1907-1926, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Imai, G., 1920-1924
  - "I" miscellaneous, 1905-1924, undated
  - Jordan, David Starr, 1901-1926, (4 folders)
  - "J" miscellaneous, 1897-1925
  - Katakura & Co., 1920-1924 See same container, Imai, G.
  - Kellogg, John Harvey, 1917-1926
  - Kellogg, Vernon L., 1900-1915, undated
  - Knudsen, H., 1898-1901, undated (Box 7)
  - "K" miscellaneous, 1891-1926, undated
  - Leib, S. F., 1896-1922
  - Lelong, B. M., 1890-1900
  - Lemmon, J. G., 1886-1904
  - de Longpré, Paul, 1899-1903, undated
  - "L" miscellaneous, 1893-1926, undated, (2 folders)
  - Maxim, Hudson, 1911-1925
  - Mills, Susan L., 1907-1908
  - Morrow, W. W., 1904-1909
  - Miller, P. Francisco, 1918-1922 (Box 8)
  - Muir, John, 1910
  - "M" miscellaneous, 1890-1926, undated, (3 folders)
  - "N" miscellaneous, 1891-1926
  - Osterhout, J. V., 1901-1904
  - "O" miscellaneous, 1901-1925, undated
  - "P" miscellaneous
    - 1898-1908
    - 1909-1926, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - "Q-R" miscellaneous, 1888-1926, undated, (3 folders)
  - Samu, Spiegel, 1893-1896
  - School children
    - 1901-1922, (2 folders)
    - 1923-1926, undated (Box 10)
  - Schull, George H., 1908-1912
  - Scientific American, 1903-1926
  - Slater, Herbert W., 1917-1925, undated
  - "S" miscellaneous, 1892-1926, undated, (4 folders)
  - "T" miscellaneous, 1891-1926, undated
  - "U-V" miscellaneous, 1896-1926, undated (Box 11)
  - Vachell, F. Harvey, 1903-1912
  - Van Deman, H. E., 1894-1905
  - Waugh, F. A., 1896-1901
  - Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1906-1914, undated
  - White Crusaders, 1909
  - Woodward, Robert S. See Container 3, Carnegie Institution of Washington
  - "W" miscellaneous, 1888-1926, undated, (3 folders)
  - "X-Y" miscellaneous, 1894-1925 (Box 12)
  - Unidentified and anonymous, 1898-1927, undated
- Speeches and Writings File, 1869-1950 (Box 12-18)
  Holograph, typewritten, near-print, and printed copies of speeches, lectures, and writings.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of speech or author. Burbank's writings are listed in one category, those by others in another.
  - By Burbank (Box 12)
    - Catalog descriptions, 1906-1911
      - Bulbs
      - Cactus
      - Cereals and other farm crops
      - Climbing vines, large
      - Blackberries
      - Deciduous trees
      - Desert plants
      - Evergreen trees (mostly conifers)
      - Ferns and mosses
      - Flowers, (3 folders)
      - Forage plants
      - Fruits
      - Fruits: vines and shrubs (Box 13)
      - Giant ornamental grasses
      - Gladioli
      - Gourds
      - Herbs, uncommon vegetables, and other economic plants
      - Legumes
      - Mistletoe, parasitic plants, etc.
      - Nuts
      - Nut trees and nuts
      - Orchids
      - Ornamental grasses and sedges
      - Palms
      - Plums
      - Succulents
      - Shrubs
      - Shrubs, ornamental
      - Solanums and physalis
      - Textile plants
      - Uncommon tropicals
      - Vegetables
      - Vegetables and garden plants
      - Water and bog plants
    - Great men, eulogies and statements, 1915-1926, undated (Box 14)
    - Lectures, Stanford University, Stanford, Calif., 1904-1906
    - Miscellany
      - Titled, A-Z, 1869-1926
      - Untitled or incomplete, 1918-1922, undated
      - Quotations
    - Printed catalogs
      - 1883-1922, (6 folders)
      - 1923-1927 (Box 15)
    - Proof Book Number 1, for Luther Burbank Society, 1913
    - Transcribed interviews with Burbank
      - By Burt C. Bean
        - pp. 1-716, (7 folders)
        - pp. 717-1918, (12 folders) (Box 16)
        - p. 1919-2356, (4 folders) (Box 17)
      - By Clark, 1914
  - By others
    - Burbank, Elizabeth Waters, 1932-1935, (2 folders)
    - Hall, Wilbur, 1941
    - Jordan, David Starr
    - Kellogg, Vernon L., 1906-1915
    - Miscellaneous
      - Printed, A-Z, 1898-1950
      - Typewritten, 1916-1935, undated
    - Poems dedicated to Burbank (Box 18)
    - De Vries, Hugo, 1904-1906, undated
    - Wickson, Edward J., 1905-1908, undated
- Notes and Sketches, 1886-1925 (Box 18-20)
  Notes and sketches made by Burbank of fruit and plant species.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Apple trees, (4 folders) (Box 18)
  - Berries, cherries, and grapes
  - Cherry trees (Box 19)
  - Crosses
  - Daisies
  - Gladioli
  - Grafting charts, vibrations, etc.
  - Grapes
  - Lilies
  - Lilies and berries
  - List of plants and seeds
  - Miscellany
  - New plums
  - Hybrids and crossings
  - Peach trees
  - Peach trees, plumcots, and nectarines, (3 folders)
  - Pear trees, (3 folders) (Box 20)
  - Plum trees, (3 folders)
  - Quince trees
  - Strawberries
  - Miscellany
- Business Records, 1871-1921 (Box 21-25)
  Account books, order books, plan books, seed and stock records, subscription books, and an inventory of Burbank's nursery operations.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of record and chronologically therein.
  - Account books (Box 21)
    - 1882-1888, (6 folders)
    - 1898-1902 (Box 22)
  - Inventory, 1871-1874
  - Order books
    - 1881-1885, (6 folders)
    - 1885-1889, (5 folders) (Box 23)
  - Plan books, 1883-1921, (5 folders) (Box 24)
  - Seed records (Box 25)
    - Domestic, 1905-1914, undated, (2 folders)
    - Foreign, 1902-1904
  - Stock records, 1887-1894
  - Subscription books, undated, (2 vols.)
- Miscellany, 1894-1922 (Box 26-40)
  Clippings, calling cards, invitations, programs, seed catalogs, membership cards, magazines, journals, printed matter, and scrapbooks.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Clippings (Box 26)
    - California earthquake, 1906
    - Miscellaneous, (4 folders)
  - Printed matter
    - Calling cards and tickets
    - Invitations
    - Journals and magazines (Box 27)
      - Century Magazine, 1905-1911, (2 folders)
      - Guide to Nature, 1910-1913
      - Miscellaneous, 1894-1922, (2 folders); (5 folders); (6 folders); (4 folders) (Box 28, Box 29, Box 30)
      - Overland Monthly, 1903-1908, (2 folders)
      - Sunset Magazine, 1901-1909, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 31)
    - Membership cards
    - Programs
    - Seed catalogs, (2 folders)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Index
    - Membership cards
    - Programs
    - Seed catalogs, (2 folders)
    - Vol. 3, 1901-1904 (Box 32)
    - Vol. 4, 1902-1905 (Box 33)
    - Vol. 5, 1905 (Box 34)
    - Vol. 6, 1905-1906 (Box 35)
    - Vol. 7, 1906-1907 (Box 36)
    - Vol. 8, 1907-1908 (Box 37)
    - Vol. 9, 1908 (Box 38)
    - Vol. 14, 1913-1917 (Box 39)
    - Vol. 17, 1915-1922 (Box 40)
- Addition, 1989 (Box 41)
  Printed matter.
  - Historic American Buildings Survey, Documentation No. CA-2254 of Gold Ridge Farm, Luther Burbank's Experimental Farm, Sebastopol, Calif., 1989 (Box 41)
- Microfilm, 1864-1964, Microfilm shelf no. 17,388 (Reel 1-2)
  Correspondence, family papers and genealogies, nursery plans and notes, financial records, scrapbooks, and miscellany retained by the Luther Burbank Home, Santa Rosa, Calif.
  Arranged and described to reflect the arrangement of the Burbank Papers in the Library of Congress.
  - Family papers (Reel 1)
    - Correspondence, 1919, undated
    - Genealogies, 1864, undated
    - Writings and anecdotes, 1921-1926, undated
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1874-1964, undated, (2 folders)
    - Bryan, Mary Baird, 1911-1912
    - Edison, Thomas A., 1915-1920
    - Keller, Helen, 1925
    - Kinsey, Alfred C., 1925
    - London, Jack, 1905
    - Scopes trial, Dayton, Tenn., [1925]
    - Wilson, Woodrow, 1916
  - Nursery plans
    - Plan books, 1881-1908, 1926, (2 vols.)
    - Plan map, 1914
    - Plant descriptions, 1908-1921
    - Plant notes, 1890, 1892, 1896
  - Financial records
    - Bank books
      - 1883-1898
      - 1902-1903, 1909-1917
    - Deeds, 1874-1913
    - Deeds and abstracts, undated, (2 folders)
    - Mortages, 1885-1888 (Reel 2)
    - Sales books, 1878-1885, (3 vols.)
  - Miscellany
    - Photographs, undated
    - "Riverside Addition," undated
    - Schools named after Burbank in California, undated
    - Printed matter, Burbank's plant contributions
    - Scrapbooks
      - Vol. 1, 1874-1895
      - Vol. 2, 1895-1904[?]